Charlotte M. Johnson papers M2196
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Charlotte M. Johnson papers
c. 1890-1928
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Johnson, Charlotte M.
Michael Brown Rare Books
M2196
3 Linear Feet (9 boxes and 5 map folders)
Biographical note
Charlotte M. "Lotte" Johnson, of Brattleboro, Vermont, was a graduate of Middlebury College, member of the Women's Union Missionary Society of America, missionary teacher, and Superintendent of the Bridgman Memorial School at West Gate, Shanghai, China, from 1890-1928.
Content Description
Materials include correspondence (both manuscript and typescript), diaries, newspapers, artwork, photographs, and ephemera created and collected by missionary teacher Charlotte Johnson. Most of the correspondence is from the time that Johnson went to China just after 1904-1914, while the diaries date from her school years (1890-1896). Much of the material relates to Johnson's missionary work in Shanghai, as well as her high school and college years at Northfield Academy and Middlebury College.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford Libraries in; 2016. Accession MSS 2017-022.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Johnson, Charlotte M.; Michael Brown Rare Books
- Outgoing letters, 1907- (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters from Katherine Jennings Abbey, 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters from Sophia W. Dauchy, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters from S.D. Doremus to C. M. Johnson and to Ms. McClean, 1908-1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters from F. L. Kow Kee Timber Co., 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letters from Annie G. Hall, 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters from Emma Gary Lee, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letters from Margaretta C. Morgan, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters from S. C. New to C. M. Johnson and to Miss Doremus, 1907-1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Incoming letters - various, 1900-1908 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Incoming letters - various, 1909-1911 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Incoming letters - various, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Incoming letters - various (includes some undated), 1913-1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letters - various (includes some undated), 1897-1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Canceled envelopes, some with notations (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Postcards (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Telegram from S. D. Doremus (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 17)
- The Woman's Union Missionary Society of America, fifty second annual report, January 1913 and fifty fourth annual report, January 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- The Missionary Link, v. 37-43, March 1906 - December 1912, with missing issues (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Missionary ephemera (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Manuscript ephemera (Box 2, Folder 4)
- School ephemera (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
- Printed ephemera (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- 1891 With Modern Authors compiled by Alice F. Stevens, Greenough, Hopkins and Cushing, Boston (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Memorandum and account books: expense accounts from time at Middlebury College, 1898-1903 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Diaries (3) when Charlotte M. Johnson was 15-21 years old, attending Northfield Academy as well as teaching. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Chinese booklets (3) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Chinese envelopes, red, with some writing (Half-box 4, Folder 1)
- Chinese letters (Half-box 4, Folder 2)
- Chinese receipts (Half-box 4, Folder 3)
- Three glass plate negatives (Half-box 4, Folder 4)
- The China Press: August 14, 1912; October 26, 1913; October 28 - November 1, 1913 (Oversize-box 5, Folder 1)
- The China Press: November 16 and November 22, 1913 (very brittle) (Oversize-box 5, Folder 2)
- The China Press: January 21, 1914; February 1, 1914; February 3 - February 7, 1914 (Oversize-box 5, Folder 3)
- The Shanghai Times: October 11, 1910; Manitou Springs Daily Journal: June 25, 1915; Beverly Evening Times: November 5, 1912; The Rocky Mountain News: June 30, 2015 (very brittle) (Oversize-box 5, Folder 4)
- Articles or select pages from the following newspapers: Springfield Union; Boston Evening Transcrip; The North American; Deerfield Valley Times; The State: Columbia S. C.; The Columbia Record; The Brattleboro Daily News; The Reformer: Brattleboro; The New York Times; The New York Herald; The Home News; Middlebury Register (Oversize-box 6, Folders 1-3)
- The Monthly Record, April 1904; Southern Christian Advocate, February 13, 1913; The Wellspring, vol. LI no. 7, 1894; Cottager and Ready Record, December 15, 1892; The Household; articles from The Evengelist and The Watchman, September 16, 1897; The Congregationalist, August 15, 1895 (Oversize-box 6, Folder 4)
- Map of the United States: template for spoon rack (Box 6)
- Articles or pages from The New York Daily Tribune; The Sunday Herald, Boston; The Whitehall Chronicle; The Vermont Phoenix (Map-folder 7)
- The North China Daily News: Incomplete issues of September 20, 1905; December 23, 1905; March 10, 1906; September 4, 1906; September 7, 1906; March 1, 1911; September 28, 1911; October 4, 1911; November 15, 1912; August 15, 1913; September 2, 1913 (Map-folder 8-10)
- Notification of service at Christian church (in Chinese) (Map-folder 11)
- Northfield Conference in Massachussetts, 1894: newspaper articles pasted into booklet (Flat-box 12)
- Reproductions of art of Chinese images (Flat-box 12)
- Student artwork (Flat-box 12)
- Photograph of class of chidren, Chang-su-ho-garden photographer, Shanghai (Flat-box 12)
- To the editor of the North-China Daily News, two published letters: Mr. Ku Hung-Ming on the situation, and Revolutionary literature (Othertype 13)
- Notarized letter of change of contractor to complete Brigdman school building (Othertype 13)
- Letter to Miss Johnson from Clara Alward, 1900-03-08 (Othertype 13)
- Pledge for Teacher of the Bridgman Memorial Home, Shanghai, China (Othertype 13)
- Unusually long letter in Chinese signed by Charlotte Johnson and D. H. Davis (Othertype 13)
- Printed document (?) in Chinese (Othertype 13)
- Chinese artifacts: calling cards, ribbons, pin, jade pieces, tea box, decorative box (Box 14)